[{"question":"Which of the following is not a function of  parts.  mitotic cell division in animals?","a":"Asexual reproduction","b":"Growth","c":"Repair and damage organ","d":"Production of gamates","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"In G-phase of cell division:","a":"RNA and proteins are synthesised for cell growth and subsequent DNA replication  divisions.  .","b":"DNA and proteins are synthesised.","c":"Formation of RNA and protein continues algae, cells undergo mitosis repeatedly without subsequently undergoing cytokinesis. What would result from this?  (b) DNA and proteins are synthesised.  22.  for spindle formation and cell growth.","d":"Cell undergoes duplication","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"If there are 22 chromosomes in the nucleus of  Thinking  a toad skin cell, a toad egg would contain chromosomes.","a":"22","b":"44","c":"11","d":"33","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Cell division is a normal process in organisms.  most lacking nuclei.  but sudden and rapid mitosis of cells in an organ may result into :","a":"New organ ","b":"Gastrula","c":"Zygote ","d":"Cancer","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"A plant has number of chromosome groups  arranged at equatorial plane of metaphase-1  Chiasma  whose 2n = 50; the number of chromosomes visible will be :","a":"100","b":"25","c":"50","d":"75","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"A drug called colchicine is shown to interferespecially with spindle microtubules formationduring mitosis. This result would be:","a":"dehydration of chromosomes","b":"despiralisation of chromosomes","c":"arrest of chromosome movements","d":"arrest of centrioles movements","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Chromosomes in salivary gland cells of Drosophila larvae are :","a":"Polythene ","b":"Lampbrush type ","c":"B-type","d":"Normal type ","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Crossing over during meiosis occurs at four strand stage. This is proved by the observation that:","a":"rarely all four gametes resulting from a  meiotic division could be recombinants","b":"usually only two gametes resulting from meiotic division could be recombinants","c":"chaismata are seen only at the four strand stage .","d":"occasionally none of the four gametes resulting  metaphase plate.  from meiosis could be a recombinant","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Meiosis and mitosis differ from each other because in meiosis .","a":"The four nuclei formed are not similar to parental ones ","b":"Homologous chromosomes pair are exchange parts ","c":"Number of chromosomes gets halved.","d":"All of the above","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Non-Sister chromatids:","a":"cross over during prophase I of meiosis","b":"separate during the first meiotic division.  13.  (c) are produced during S phase between","c":"are produced during S phase between cell division ","d":"cross over during prophase II of meiosis.","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"In some organisms, such as certain fungi and (c) Formation of RNA and protein continues algae, cells undergo mitosis repeatedly without subsequently undergoing cytokinesis. What would result from this?","a":"A decrease in chromosome number","b":"Inability to duplicate DNA","c":"Division of the organism into many cells. most lacking nuclei","d":"Large cells containing many nuclei.","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"At what phase of meiosis there are two cells.  (c) Crossing over  each with sister chromatids aligned at the  (d) Transcription  spindle equator?","a":"Anaphase II","b":"Metaphase II","c":"Metaphase 1 ","d":"Anaphase 1","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Who stated that new cells develop from pre- existing cells?","a":"Remak","b":"Virchow","c":"Prevost and Dumas","d":"Strasburger","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"One chromosome of a homologous pair carries (c) division of chromosomes during anaphase  the genes J and K. The other chromosome of the pair carries the genes j and k at corresponding loci. Crossing over results in exchange of chromosome segments and production of gametes with new combinations of genes. A chromosomes appear: recombinant type gamete resulting from this crossover might contain  of mitosis.  (d) orientation of chromosomes during metaphase  I of meiosis.  36.  During pachytene stage of  meiosis, the  (a) Single stranded  Critical","a":"Genes J and k","b":"Genes j and K","c":"Genes 1 and j","d":"Genes and k","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Chiasmata are formed during meiosis:","a":"before metaphase 1","b":"after metaphase 1","c":"during prophase 2","d":"during metaphase 2","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Replication of centriole occurs during:","a":"Early anaphase ","b":"Mid metaphase ","c":"Late metaphase ","d":"Interphase","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Recombinant nodules are found during","a":"Anaphase ","b":"Prophase ","c":"Telophase ","d":"Metaphase ","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Prophase is longer in:","a":"Mitosis","b":"Meiosis","c":"Equal in both","d":"Amitosis","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"In telophase of mitosis, the mitotic spindle  D. The plane of IV. Cell divides to give  breaks down and nuclear membranes form  alignment of two daughter cells.  This is essentially the opposite of what happens  chromosomes  in:  Tricky","a":"Prophase","b":"Interphase","c":"Metaphase","d":"S phase","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Centromere is required for:","a":"Movement of chromosomes towards poles","b":"Cytoplasmic cleavage","c":"Crossing over","d":"Transcription","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Most cells divide if they receive the proper signal at a checkpoint in the  ","a":"M ","b":"G1","c":"S ","d":"G2","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which of the following does not lead to genetic variability?","a":"random fertilisation","b":"crossing over during meiosis","c":"division of chromosomes during anaphase of mitosis ","d":"orientation of chromosomes during metaphasei of meiosis ","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"During pachytene stage of  meiosis, the chromosomes appear ","a":"Single stranded","b":"Four stranded","c":"Six stranded","d":"Eight stranded","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which of the following statements related to G0 stage of the cell cycle are correct ","a":"It is a quiescent stage","b":"In this phase, cell cycle is stopped.","c":"Go cells do not grow or proliferate but metabolically active ","d":"G cells can divide  in response to some stimulus ","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"phases/stages of cell cycle with few parts 45. Meiosis which occur at the time of spore  mix.  labelled as 1, 2, 3 & 4.Which one of the following is the correct These cells are probably considered in:  indication of the stage phase in the cell cycle?  (a) G-phase (b) S-phase (d) Go-phase  (a) 3-Karyokinesis (b","a":"3-Karyokinesis","b":"4-Synthetic phase","c":"1-Cytokinesis","d":"2-Metaphase","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Pick out the correct sequence of two main events in mitosis","a":"Karyokinesis is followed by cytokinesis","b":"Cytokinesis is followed by karyokinesis","c":"Karyokines is followed by separation of the daughter cell","d":"Cytokinesis is followed by separation of the daughter cell ","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Cell division in blue green algae is similar to that in ","a":"Bacteria","b":"Brown algae","c":"Green algae","d":"Higher plants","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Strasburger is famous for","a":"discovery of cell division","b":"proposing the term nucleoplasm","c":"proposing the term cytoplasm","d":"All of the above ","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"When synapsis is complete all along the  (a) 50 chromosomes, each consisting of 2 chromatids  chromosome, the cell is said to have entered a stage called ","a":"Zygotene","b":"Pachytene","c":"Diplotene","d":"Diakenisis ","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"In pachytene stage of meiosis the chromosomes appear ","a":"Single stranded","b":"Double stranded","c":"Three stranded","d":"Four stranded","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Choose the event of cell cycle which shows the importance of synapsis and the formation of  stage of the cell cycle are correct?  (i). It is a quiescent stage. (ii). In this phase, cell cycle is stopped.  chiasmata.  Critical","a":"An increase in the variation of progeny occur ","b":"Reciprocal exchange of chromosomal selection occur ","c":"The DNA on homologous chromosomes.","d":"All of the above ","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Meiosis which occur at the time of spore formation is called ","a":"Zygotic meiosis","b":"Haplontic meiosis","c":"Terminal meiosis","d":"Intermediate meiosis","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"The cellular structure which disappear during mitosis is ","a":"Plasma membrane","b":"Nuclear membrane","c":"Mitochondria","d":"Nuclear membrane and nucleolus","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Mature nerve cells cannot undergo cell division.  Which one of the following is the correct These cells are probably considered in","a":"G2-phase","b":"S-phase ","c":"Mitosis ","d":"G0-phase","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"After meiosis I, the two chromatids of a chromosomes are ","a":"Genetically similar","b":"Genetically different","c":"There occurs only one chromatid in cach chromosomes ","d":"None of the above","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Fully differentiated cells which do not divide","a":"G1-phase","b":"G2-phase","c":"S-phase","d":"G0-phase","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"A zoologist examined an intestine cell from a  crayfish and counted 200 chromosomes, cach  41. Strasburger is famous for:  consisting of 2 chromatids, at prophase I of  mitosis. What would he expect to see in cach  (a) discovery of cell division (b) proposing the term nucleoplasm  of the four cells at telophase II of meiosis if he  looked in the crayfish ovary?  (e) proposing the term cytoplasm  Critical","a":"50 chromosomes, each consisting of 2 chromotids","b":"50 chromosomes, each consisting of 1 chromotid ","c":"100 chromosomes, each consisting of 2 chromotid ","d":"100 chromosomes, each consisting of I  appear:  chromatid","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Meiosis in AaBb will produce gametes;","a":"AB, aB, Ab,ab","b":"AB,ab","c":"Aa,bb","d":"Aa,Bb","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Which one of the following list contain the  C. Spindle fibres III. Interphase  attach to  correct order of meiotic events?  Critical  kinetochores  Thinking","a":"Separation of sister chromatids,  D. Movement of  IV. Metaphase  recombination, formation of the synaptonemal complex, separation of homo logous chromosomes ","b":"Separation of homologous chromosomes, formation of the synaptonemal complex,  chromatids  towards  opposite poles (a) A - II; B - III; C - IV; D - I  (b) A-III; B-II :C-L; D - IV  recombinationseparation of sister chromotid ","c":"Formation of synaptonemal complex  (c) A - 1; B - III C - II; D - IV  recombination, separation of sister chromatids,  (d) A-IV; B-III; C-ID-II 60. When dividing cells are observed under a light  separation of homologous chromosomes ","d":"Formation of the synaptonemal complex, recombination, separation of homologous chromosomes, separation of sister chromatids","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"\"Bouquet-stage\" occur in which sub stages of prophase 1 ","a":"Leptotene","b":"Zygotene","c":"Pachytene","d":"Diplotene","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Which of the following human cells unlikely to  see dividing?","a":"Nerve cell","b":"Skin cell","c":"Cancer cell","d":"Cell from an embryo ","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Meiosis takes place in:","a":"Apical meristem","b":"Intercalary meristem","c":"Reproductive cells","d":"Vegetative cells","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which division maintains genetic similarity","a":"Mitosis ","b":"Meiosis ","c":"Amitosis ","d":"Reduction division ","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"When dividing cells are observed under a light  separation of homologous chromosomes.  (d) Formation of the synaptonemal complex, recombination, separation of homologous chromosomes, separation of sister chromatids.  microscope, chromosomes become visible in:","a":"Interphase ","b":"S-phase ","c":"Prophase ","d":"G1-phase","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which cell division is found during cleavage","a":"Amitosis ","b":"Mitosis ","c":"Closed mitosis ","d":"Meiosis","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"If a grasshopper cell contained 200 units of (c) Metaphase-1  DNA during G, what would be the quantity of (d) Metaphase-IT 70. In mitosis nucleolus and nuclear membrane  DNA in one of the  grasshopper cells at the end  of telophase II of meiosis","a":"50 unit ","b":"100unit ","c":"Between 50 and 100 unit","d":"200unit ","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"If the n-16 in plant cell then what is possible in Toughnut  metaphase-I of meiosis?","a":"32 bivalents","b":"16 tetravalents","c":"16 bivalents","d":"32 bivalents","hint":"","correct":"c"}]